Ines Arevalo Sanchez

Email: inesas79@gmail.com **Telephone:** +34 617 278 833

PROFILE

10 years working in international development, setting up measurement frameworks, conducting and supervising research, training and building capacity. Offering proven experience: microfinance, poverty measurement, social performance and enterprise development. Independent performer under little supervision, but strong team spirit with great attention to detail. Native Spanish-speaker, proficient English.

KEY SKILLS

Monitoring, Evaluation and Research

- Developed a monitoring, evaluation and learning (MEL) framework, identifying and developing suitable tools and indicators for the assessment of the Aga Khan Agency for Microfinance (AKAM) clients.
- Guided and supervised more than 50 AKAM market research and MEL activities, by advising on sampling approaches, reviewing tools, indicators, datasets and reports and conducting data analysis as needed.
- Developed and used monitoring tools to assess the performance of 23 community based microcredit units (MCU) and to report on the effectiveness of the Natural Forest Management Project (NFMP).

Social Performance

- Supported AKAM field teams during the development and pilot of the Progress out of Poverty Index (PPI) in 10 countries. Worked with the local teams to set out the procedures to integrate the PPI into the daily microfinance operations. Built the capacity of local teams on PPI data analysis and reporting.
- Developed customer satisfaction and exit surveys for AKAM. Guided the field teams from 10 countries through the survey process, from adapting the surveys to the local context, reviewing data analysis to supporting the teams to draw lessons learnt and implications for products and operations.
- Supervised the implementation of more than 100 in-depth interviews in 4 countries to assess changes in the quality of life of AKAM's clients.
- Lead the development of a database and worked with 10 AKAM entities to set out the procedures for the collection, storing and management of client-level data.
- Guided five AKAM entities through the implementation of the SMART Campaign self-assessment tool on client protection principles. Consolidated findings and recommendations.

Training and Capacity Building

- Developed and managed an online training on microfinance, with a focus on client assessment, product development and programme evaluation for Coordinadora de ONGs para el Desarrollo España.
- Conducted more than 40 training sessions with NFMP's target groups on microcredit and MCU procedures.
- Built the research capacity of staff from AKAM entities by developing research guides and toolkits, providing on-thejob support and delivering face to face as well as online training.

Project Management

- Worked with AKAM's field entities and NFMP project staff to develop tailor-made strategies, work plans, budgets, grant proposals (with a focus on logical frameworks), request for proposals and annual reports.
- Supported NFMP's exit strategy, by designing the final framework and handover agreements, meeting with stakeholders, including donors, and coordinating the final disbursement of the Microcredit Fund.

Computer skills

- Proficient user of Microsoft Office tools (Word, Excel, PowerPoint and Outlook) & Internet browsers.
- Knowledge of **SPSS**, **Stata** and Microfit (software applications for data analysis).

WORK EXPERIENCE

Independent Consultant Coordinadora ONG para el Desarrollo - España, Madrid, Spain		2016
Research and Social Performance Consultant Aga Khan Agency for Microfinance (AKAM), Geneva, Switzerland		2010 – 2016
Microcredit Unit Capacity Building and Support Expert GITEC Consult GmbH for the Natural Forest Management Project, Beijing, China		2008 – 2010
Client Assessment Research Fellow FINCA International, Mexico		2009
External Consultant – International Department Grandall Legal Group, Beijing, China		2008
Microcredit Junior Expert EU-China Natural Forest Management Project, Baoxing, China		2006 – 2007
Research Assistant Centre for Research on the Wider Benefits of Learning, University of London, United Kingdom		2006
Research Assistant Claydon Gescher Associates, Beijing, China		2005
Purchase Agent Rentandramo S.L., Beijing, China		2004 – 2005
Tutor Microeconomics and Macroeconomics Academia Montero Espinosa, Madrid, Spain		2003 – 2004
QUALIFICATIONS		
MA in Development Economics	University of Sussex	2006
BSc in Economics	Universidad Complutense de Madrid, University of Sussex	2003
TRAINING		
Training of Trainers on Designing and Implementing Quality Surveys Statistical Services Centre at the University of Reading, United Kingdom		2014
Impact Assessment International NGO Training and Research Centre, London, United Kingdom		2014
Statistics Made Simple (eSMS) Statistical Services Centre at the University of Reading, United Kingdom		2013
Certified Microfinance Trainer Asian Development Bank Institute and the Tokyo Development Learning Center of the World Bank		2008
SELECTED PUBLICATIONS		
Monitoring and Managing Financial and Social Performance (co-authored) in <i>The New Microfinance Handbook</i> , ed. by Joanna Ledgerwood. Washington: The World Bank		2013
The Wider Benefits of Vocational Learning (co-authored) in: The International Handbook of Technical and Vocational Education and Training, ed. by Rupert MacLean and Prof. David Wilson. Bonn: UNESCO-UNEVOC International Centre		2007
Green Microcredit for Forest Fringe Villages April Paper presented at the 'First NFMP Regional Dissemination Workshop on Approaches and Technologies for Sustainable Natural Forest Management'		2007